Plotly is a package of powerful
visualization tools to use with R.
And in many respects,
Plotly is an alternative to ggplot with
a relatively easy to learn syntax for
generating many of the same kinds of plots
that we've created so far in this course.
Plotly is also notable for
how easy it is to make figures
interactive using this tool.
With Plotly, and especially in
conjunction Shiny and flexdashboards,
you can replicate many of
the interactive figures of
visualization software
like Tableau using R.
If you really want to maximize
your visualization skills using R,
you should take the time to
learn Plotly in its entirety.
And with what we've learned so far,
it shouldn't be especially difficult for
you to transfer your knowledge about how
to code in R to use this new package.
However, in this course, we just don't
have time to cover everything, so
we prioritize ggplot over Plotly.
The best resources for
learning Plotly are online.
Carson Sievert has a textbook that you
can purchase that provides a really nice
introduction.
And there's a free version of this
available online at plotly-r.com.
There's also a great set of reference
materials available at plotly.com.
If you have time,
it's a great idea to learn to use Plotly,
drawing on skills you
developed in this class.
Fortunately though, you don't have to
learn all of Plotly in order to make use
of it and to improve the visualizations
that we've created in GG plot.
Plotly has a special function that
interacts with ggplot figures to
make those figures interactive, and
appropriately, it's called ggplotly.
The basic usage of ggplotly is very easy.
And all you have to do is create
a ggplot figure and then take it and
use it within the ggplot function in order
to use the special tools of ggplotly.
So let me show you how to do that.
Follow along with the R code that's
associated with this video, and
I'm using an adapting code
here from plotly.com.
First, you install the libraries that we
need and load those up, and then here,
I'm going to make some fake data,
pulling data from a normal distribution.
This is what we've seen in the past.
We'll make a really simple
scatter plot using ggplot and
save that to the object
p into R environment.
And from there, we just wrapped that
function ggplotly around the ggplot object
that we've created, and
we say that to the object fig.
Now if you run fig in RStudio,
you'll get the ggplot figure, but
with the extra bells and
whistles of Plotly.
Now we see that if we hover
the cursor over a data point,
we'll get a pop up box that
displays data about that point.
And you'll see that the plot
includes zooming and
panning functions that you don't have
with a traditional static ggplot figure.
You can follow this exact same approach
for many different ggplot figures.
And it's worthwhile to spend some time
playing with line charts, bar charts,
heat maps, and the other kinds of figures
that we've created in the course so far.
And to see what kind of interactivity
comes up when you feed the ggplotly
function a ggplot figure.
You can also go and make all the same
kinds of aesthetic tweaks that we've done
before, changing labels and colors, and
that sort of thing within the ggplot
figure before you feed it into ggplotly.