Another new trick that you can
do with Plotly is to animate
your figures similarly to how
we worked with gganimate.
Like gganimate, Plotly works to
animate your figures
by creating frames
of the animation based on
cycling through some value in
your data and then redrawing
the figure for each
different value.
This is quite easy to do.
So to give you an example
here I will start with
drawing a static
scatter plot using
geom points and the
congressional effectiveness data
that we've been working with
in several previous examples.
This should all be very
familiar to you by now,
but you can review the
code here if you need to.
What this ggplot figure does,
is it plots legislative
effectiveness on the y-axis and
seniority on the x-axis with
the points colored by party.
Legislative effectiveness is
just a score that is intended
to measure how
productive members of
Congress are at making laws,
and higher means more productive,
and again what we would expect,
is that members that
become more senior,
that had been in the chamber
longer should be more
productive and have a
higher legislative
effectiveness score.
So if we whip this up, we have
a scatter plot for all members of
Congress across all the years
in Congresses in this data set.
If I wanted to animate
this figure to
show change across years,
I could wrap the
entire ggplot command
in the ggplotly function,
and then I can add an option
in the aesthetics here that
sets frame to the year
column in my data.
So this is going to redraw
the figure over and over
again based on the different
years in the data set.
When you do this, ggplotly
creates the figure,
and then you have this play
button down here that will
animate the figure and
redraw it year by year.
You'll notice that this
animation is pre-jumpy though.
If you wanted to smooth it out,
you could introduce what's called
object constancy to the figure.
This will cause points to
move from their point in
the previous frame rather than
being redrawn from scratch
every single time.
What I'm doing here is
adding in the name of
each member of Congress
as the ID here,
because this is constant
across multiple years and
the data set as you track
individual members across time.
When you add this and
rerun the animation,
you'll see that it smooth out
and you're actually able to track
some of the outlier members
across Congresses, across years.
In terms of saving or
sharing a plotly figure,
you can export a
plotly figure from
the RStudio viewer as
an image and you'll get
a static image file.
Alternatively, you can
save it as a DOTHTML file,
and then if you open that
up in a web browser,
it preserves the interactive
elements of the figure,
and then you could embed
this in either web page or
other kinds of
documents depending
on what you're trying to produce.
If you want to publish a
plotly figure to the web,
you can actually do this from
the viewer window as well,
and if you click on
the publish button,
you can publish the
visualization directly to RPubs.
You'll need to create an account,
though once you do this,
the HTML file will upload to
your RPubs website and
you can share the link
however of you like.
For more about publishing
your visualizations to
the web and sharing them,
you'll have to take
the next course
in this specialization.