In the next series of videos,
we're going to work
our way through
a number of different
kinds of figures,
getting a real workout with
ggplot and some
associated libraries.
The goal of these videos
is to give you practice
with making a wide
variety of figures.
So for these videos, and
really throughout this course,
we're not going to do as much
emphasis on data wrangling,
but we're just going
to make a lot of
figures and get some practice.
We'll start with some
variations on scatter plots.
Many of you probably have some
basic training in statistics,
or at least you're
familiar with the idea of
putting a trend line
through a scatter plot.
This allows you to
get a better sense
of the relationship between
two variables than
what you might be able
to get from just looking
at a cloud of points.
For example, I will use a set of
survey data here that we've
used in previous classes,
courses from
the Cooperative Congressional
Election Survey.
In that survey data,
there are questions about
the educational level of
survey respondents
in the United States
and their political ideology.
If you pay attention
to US politics at all,
or really to politics in
many different
parts of the world,
you might be aware that an
increased level of education
is often associated with
greater political liberalism.
In the survey data,
the variable ideo5 captures
political ideology,
with five being the most
conservative and one
being the most liberal.
The educ variable captures
education level with 16
being the highest and
one being the lowest.
So we ought to see a
negative correlation
between these two variables.
It's hard to assess
from a scatter plot
what that relationship
really looks like.
But drawing a best fit line
gives you a better sense for it.
We add a best fit line to
the scatter plot here
with geom_smooth.
There are a lot of
different approaches for
drawing a best fit line but
the default that geom_smooth
uses is the loess curve.
If you're statistically inclined,
you can select several
different methods
for drawing that line,
like a linear model or a
generalized linear model,
and you can also change
the confidence intervals
drawn around the line.
But be very careful with this if
you're not
statistically inclined,
because doing
statistical inference
with this kind of
approach is pretty dicey.
Exploratory analysis,
however, is fine and
so if you want to draw
some best fit lines,
you scatter plots
to get a sense for
the data just sort
of an intuition,
that's an okay thing to do.
In addition to a best fit line,
another way to use
scatter plots for
exploratory visualization is to
use a scatter plot matrix,
which will show you the
bivariate relationship
between several different
variables in your data at once.
The library GGally has
a handy tool for creating
a scatter plot matrix.
These lines of code have created
some simple fake data with
variable one and variable two
being tightly correlated and
the third variable being
negatively correlated
with variable one.
When we put these together into
a table and we feed that
into the function ggpairs,
it generates a scatter
plot matrix for
us showing the distribution
of the variables,
the bivariate scatter plots,
and the correlation coefficients
for each of the variables pairs.
If you want to modify the look
of the scatter plots with
the density plots in
a scatter plot matrix
that you make like this,
you can write custom functions
for the plotting functions,
and then you can include those in
the ggpairs function using
a lower and diagonal arguments.
This is the way that you can
control color and fill and
other aspects of
the visualization.
A related way to
dry in a plot for
correlations is a shaded
correlation matrix.
In the ggcorrplot package,
the ggcorrplot function
will generate this for us.
Here I'm selecting a few
variables from the survey data,
I calculate correlation
coefficients for
them and I generate
the correlation plot
using ggcorrplot.
ggcorrplot has a number of
different options within it
for modifying the colors and
other visual features at the plot
and you can access those if
you look at the help file,
and you can also apply
a ggtheme if you like,
if you recall doing this
from the previous course.
Beyond summarizing
bivariate relationships,
you can also modify
figures that you make with
geom_point to compare values
across units of observation,
kind of like a bar plot.
In fact, many professional data
visualizers prefer these kinds of
plots to bar charts because
of their visual simplicity.
One figure we're
talking about here is
called a cleveland dot plot,
and to give you an
example of this,
I'll draw on the data
from law about lawmaking
in the US Congress that we've
used in previous courses.
Here, I'm selecting a
sample of members from
the 114th congress and
what I want to do is compare
their legislative effectiveness,
which is summarized by the
variable les in the data.
Again, higher les values mean
more legislative
productivity for the member,
so we're basically going to
compare sort of how good of
a law maker a set of members
are by seeing how
productive they are.
In my ggplot function,
I set the data and I do
the aesthetic mapping,
so to the x-axis is my
outcome of interests
and my y-value is the
units of comparison.
When I add geom_point to this,
I get a single point analogous
to the top of a bar chart.
These next lines, I'm doing
modifications to
the theme function
to drop some of the
white vertical lines
and adding some dashed
horizontal lines,
and I also changed the
point size, the labels,
and I reorder the
units on the y-axis by
the value of the outcome
variable in descending order.
With those modifications, we get
a nice refined minimal
plot for comparison.
Finally, a
close-related variation
of this dot plot is
called a lollipop plot,
try saying that three times fast,
and it's even more
similar to a bar plot.
To make a lollipop figure,
I flipped the y and x-axis in
my aesthetic mapping
and I used geom_points,
but rather than drop
the grid-lines,
I use geom underscore
segment to draw lines
that connect from
the x-axis at the y value of
zero so that the bottom of that,
to the y value for the
variable of interest.
So going up for each
category across.
Again, this is just the
very refined simple way
of making a bar plot essentially.