By this point, we've done
a wide range of
figures in ggplot.
So I think you probably
have a good sense for
how powerful the
toolkit you develop is,
for making data visualizations.
I have just a handful of
miscellaneous other figures
to show you in this video,
and then in the next portion of
the course will
cover spatial data.
A pretty common kind of
visualization that you
see that it's good for
showing parts of a whole
world connections between
different categories and data
is called an alluvial diagram.
This is one of those figures
that you kind of have
to make to really understand.
Let's go ahead and get started.
I'm going to create
fake data here about
student performance in classes.
I have 21 students divided
into three groups of students.
The students are men and women,
and they get grades of
high pass, pass or fail.
It takes quite a bit of
wrangling to generate all that.
So pause the video here and step
through the lines of
code if you need to.
The important thing is to
get to the final table here,
and the row of this table
tells you how many males and
females and each group got
each grade in the course.
An alluvial diagram
is going to show
you how these
categories relate to
each other and how
collectively at all makes
up part of the whole.
This is something that you just,
again kind of have to do
in order to understand.
So bear with me and let's
power through this.
The Package ggalluvial,
another one is helper
packages for ggplot,
to provide some specialized
tools that we need.
We start simply with a
ggplot function and data.
The aesthetics here
are little unusual
because it's the
specialized package.
We have to set axis1 to the group
ID and axis2 to the grades,
and y to n,
which is a calculated count
of how many males or females
students in each group got
which grades in the class.
Are you confused yet?
I know it's a little
hard to follow, but again,
just keep going with me and
then we can come back and you
can review to put
the pieces together,
after you see the
finished product.
Once you have that set up,
you can add geom_alluvium.
You're going to start
to see this flow and
connections between
these categories.
Now, obviously this
doesn't break out
the categories very clearly.
So we have to add
geom_stratum to make this
a little bit clearer,
and to help even further,
we can add text to the figure
using the geom_text command,
setting the stat as stratum
and the label in static.
Like any other ggplot, we
can also add some colors.
Now, I just blasted through
that really quickly,
and this is really kind
of a special usage at
ggplot tools that you just
can't figure out on your own.
You're going to
have to consult the
ggalluvium documentation
to really get
a handle on the
internal logic for
how the pieces of this
figure go together.
There's just no replacement
for going and very
carefully reading through
and doing it on your own,
and trying to walk through it.
However, if you
follow the examples
that are in the documentation,
you should be able to
piece together the figure,
especially if your data are
formatted in the right way,
aligned with the models that you
find in the documentation.
So again, going back
to mete learning,
which you've been
talking about since
the beginning of this course.
What you want to do,
is find an example,
work through the
example carefully,
and understand the
internal logic for that
and then start to look at
your own data and figure
out how to map that
on to the example that
you were working with.
Let me show you what
other fancy figure
in case you're not
confused already,
and that's a pack circle plot.
A pack circle plot
is sort of like
an alternative to
a barplot because
it allows you to
compare values across
units and see parts of a whole.
The library pack circle provides
the function that we need
to make our circle plot.
What I'm going to do here is to
compare legislative
effectiveness or
productivity in 25 members
of congress during
the 114th Congress.
Again, legislative
effectiveness more or less
measures how productive
member is it making
laws and we're going to
compare and see how productive
these members are
relative to each
other into a 114th Congress.
This is just the exact same thing
that we did in the lolly plot.
The lolly, again, the lollipop
plot a few videos ago.
We're just going to show
the information in
a different way.
What we're going to do is
draw a series of circles of
different sizes with the
radii of the circles
indicating the magnitude of
the legislative
effectiveness score for
each member in a 114th Congress.
A member that's very
productive will have
a really big circle,
and then we're there's
not as productive
will have a small circle.
To start we use a function
in the package to get
the measurement for
the circle's based on
the legislative
effectiveness column,
the LES column of the data,
and the output here provides
the x and y points
which are going
to be the center of the
circles on our xy-plane,
along with the radius
for each circle.
So with that data, you could
imagine going and putting a pin
in a point on the figure
and drawing the circle around it.
Now that we have
this information,
we're going to put it
back into our data using
the "Add Column" function
here, and from there,
we use circle layout
vertices to generate
even more geometric information
which ggplot is going to
use to draw the edges of
the circular polygons.
Because of course a circle is
just a polygon with
infinite sides.
From here, we're
going to call ggplot,
and we're going to add the
geom_polygon function,
which is going to
draw our circle here,
setting the data
to the information
about the circles which we
created and saying that x and y
values to the center
of those circles.
This is from that
object a few lines ago.
We have to set here it's
a group, aesthetic ID,
as well as the fill to a
factorized version of the ID.
For aesthetic purposes,
we're going to set
the transparency
using alpha here.
Then we add geom texts
to provide the labels
and we do a little
additional visual tweaking.
Now this creates a
really cool plot,
and there's a certain
visual flair to this.
But again, it displays
the same information as
a bar chart would or a lollipop
plot, just formatted differently.
I wouldn't seriously
expect you to
follow all the details here,
but if you wanted to use this
figure on your own work,
again you can consult
the documentation and using
the tools you developed,
you could piece it together,
and go through the
different components
of this figure and make
it work with your data.
Now we come to a somewhat
anticlimactic end
to all this stream
of visualizations.
You might be wondering,
where are the pie charts?
While actually pie charts
are kind of disfavored
among many data
visualization specialist.
So I'm not emphasizing
them in the course.
The problem is that
humans are not very good
at comparing angles on the fly,
so pie charts can lead
to bad inference.
But if you have to
make a pie chart,
just use base R and
the pi function,
just as demonstrated here.
This is pretty simple by
comparison to everything
we've just done,
but you have so many skills now,
there's no need to settle
for less than the best.