Today, we get started
with making maps in R.
In this video, we're going to
focus just on drawing maps, and
then we'll move on down the road
to organizing geographic data, and
mapping data in subsequent videos.
To really simplified things,
any geospatial visualization that
you draw in R requires two things.
First, you have to draw the map
using some kind of data
that directs R to draw the polygon
shapes that constitute the map.
Then you add information to your map that
you will use to plot color and marks.
And in that sense, it's the same
basic logic that we've used for
ggplot figures so far.
The key thing is to have datasets
that link that geographic data with
the substantive information that
you want to put on the plot.
This is all pretty abstract, so
let's just jump right in with
a straightforward example here.
The Maps package in R contains a set
of maps of the United States and
the world drawn using longitude and
latitude data.
Obviously, there are a lot of other
geographic entities that you might want to
draw a map for.
But with the World map and the USA map
with the individual states you can
accomplish a lot of the mapping tasks,
and get an idea for how to do this.
Let's just make a map already and
this will start making more sense.
To start, I said we need to get
the data for R to draw the map.
And in the Maps package there's a command
called Map Data that can be used
to retrieve these pre baked maps that
are included in the software package.
Let's take a look at
the help file here for
Map Data, and we see that in this
command the first input is map, and
this asks us to specify the map from
the package that we want R to draw.
And we see here in the help file that
the options are for US county, France,
Italy, New Zealand, US states, and
two different versions of a World map.
Unfortunately, we don't have other
administrative subunits of the other
countries in this database.
And this is why you're going to have
to go out and grab some of this data
on your own in the future if you want
to map other kinds of geographic units.
Now let's take a look at the World map
data that is baked into the package.
And we do that by using the command
map_data and we have the input world,
and then we save this to
the object my_world_map.
Of course, you could name this
object whatever you like, but
my_world_map is what will use right now.
The object that is generated when
you run this line is a data frame,
and we can take a peek at it here, and see
that the important columns are the set of
latitude and longitude coordinates
that are used to draw the map.
A column of country names that correspond
with each of these geographic points,
and a group column that specifies
a group number for each country.
If you look through this entire table,
you would see that for some countries,
there are sub regions, but we are going to
worry about that for right now.
And this order column is just a sequential
vector that you can also ignore for
the current purposes.
Now that we have Map Data at our
fingertips, let's go ahead and
use that to draw a map with Ggplot.
With the Ggpplot command we
set the data to my_world_map.
And for the aesthetics,
we want longitude on the x-axis,
because longitude changes as you move
horizontally on a map, so on the x-axis.
And we set latitude to the y-axis
because latitude varies as
you move vertically on a map,
up and down on the y-axis.
We also need to set the group here to the
group column in order to get the border to
draw correctly.
Once we have these aesthetics maps,
we add geom_polygon to tell
Ggplot to draw the map for us, which
after all is just a bunch of polygons.
This is a Ggplot geom in the same sense
as points, or lines, or bar plots,
or other things that
we've done in the past.
Let's go ahead and run this and
we see that we get a map with black fill
in the countries and white border lines.
So now we have a world map and that can be
the basis for visualization, so we can add
color and dots to this in the future in
order to draw different kinds of figures.
Now, let's say that we wanted to look
at just one part of the World map,
a single country.
You can do this by setting a filter on
the Maps Data that selects only a certain
country or set of countries, and creates
a data frame with just the latitude and
longitude for those selected countries.
We use the Tidyverse Command filter as
we've done in the past for this, and
let's say that we wanted to
create a map of just Germany.
We would create a subset of the world map
data using this filter for just Germany.
Or Alternatively,
we could filter by more than one
country to draw several countries.
And it's best to use
contiguous countries here,
otherwise you get some strange
issues about projection and scaling.
So let's do a filter here with Germany and
France.
And as expected, now we get the figure
of France and Germany drawn,
because that's the only day that we
selected from the world map data.
Another approach, if you didn't
want to pick individual countries,
would be to filter the map
data by latitude in longitude,
especially zooming in on the box
that you draw on the map.
As I said, drawing these maps creates
the backbone for visualizations, and
we're going to add additional
information going further that will show
using color and shapes.
And will work on doing
that in the next video.