Now that we have
drawn maps using R,
we are ready to start
adding data to those maps.
Let's get ourselves
caught back up here,
so we'll load the
libraries we need,
and we'll make a blank
map of US states.
Let's examine the US
State map object here.
This is just a data frame
like those we've used before.
This region column
has the list of
the continental US states plus
the District of Columbia.
Now to paint data into this map,
we need to add some
data to the data frame.
To do this we merge some data
into the map data frame.
For example, let's
make up some fake data
that will correspond to each of
the states in this region column.
For demonstration purposes,
I'll just make a
sequence of letters,
and so we'll create a data
frame with three columns,
region and qual_value
for qualitative values,
and quant_value for
quantitative values.
For region, we'll make
that equal to the list of
unique names in the region
column of the map data frame.
So it's just a list of
the US states plus the
District of Columbia.
For the qualitative value,
I'll just create a sequence of
49 letters with a few repeats.
Apologies to Hawaii
and Alaska for
leaving you out here for
demonstration purposes.
You could think of
these letters as
qualitative data of some type.
For the quantitative
value column,
I'll just create a
sequence of 49 numbers.
After playing with this,
we have a letter and a number
assigned to every state,
and now we can merge the
original map data frame
with the values
that we've created.
We do this with a
left_join command.
If you're hazy about
how to use Joins,
you should check the
dplyr cheat sheet
and the reference materials
on the Tidyverse.
But region here is
a linking column,
so the corresponding qualitative
and quantitative values
are attached to every row that
matches the corresponding state
and we'll assign that
to a new object.
This is the good time to point
out that you should be very
careful when you're doing
these kind of data merges.
It's easy to have spelling or
capitalisation or spacing errors
that can really
mess up your joins,
so it's always good to check
manually and make sure
that that's working.
Now, using our newly
supplemented map data,
we use a GG plot function,
and this time we set
the aesthetic to fill,
and we'll drop the Fill
command in geom_polygon.
When we do this, what we have now
is called a choropleth with
colors filling in
the state boundaries
that correspond with
different letter values.
Because this is just a
normal GG plot function,
we can do all the same kinds of
formatting we have in the past,
like changing the color palette,
adding a title,
removing elements,
using themes, and so on.
We can also use exactly the
same approach here for adding
the continuous
quantitative data to
the map and make a
choropleth using that.
Again, you could do
all the same kinds
of refinements that
we've seen before.