Another type of map
you may want to
make is what is
called a bubble map,
where different points
vary in size or
color based on some set
of values in your data.
For instance, let's say that
you wanted to create a map that
included some of the
largest cities in Japan,
and you wanted to
vary the size of
the marks by population and
the color of the marks by
some other categorical or
quantitative variable.
Let's go ahead and
make this using
the Maps Package and a ggplot.
Open up a new R script
and we'll load the
required packages.
Let's also make a blank map of
Japan using the techniques
we've learned before.
The maps package has data on
many cities built into it,
and we can access that using
the following line of code.
Saved list of cities
to an object.
If you look at the object,
we see that it is a list of
many cities in Japan and
their corresponding
populations and
their latitude and
longitude coordinates.
Now we first map all
the cities in Japan.
To the blank map of Japan,
we add a geom_point function,
and when we make a
bubble plot like this.
We don't need to merge
the point data into
the map DataFrame.
Instead, we specify
the data specifically,
once again in the
geom_point function,
and then we specify
longitude and latitude.
Although we use a
group command in
the original aesthetic mapping,
we don't need one here,
so we just set it to null.
Just for some variety,
we are going to
set the color here to red.
Recall here that we
don't set the color in
the original ggplot function
or set it to a value in the data,
in the aesthetics function.
Because for now, we don't want
the color of the points to
vary in conjunction with
any value in the data.
We just unconditionally want
all the points to be red.
When we plot this,
we see that we now
have points for all
the cities in Japan,
at least the ones that
we have data for.
There are a lot of points
in the map though,
so we might want a smaller
subset of cities to display.
We can filter the cities to
select only those cities in
Japan with populations
above 500,000.
Population is contained
in the 'pop column',
so filter for greater than
500,000 in that
column and map again.
If you want to add more
information to these points,
we can change the size
and color of the points,
mapping them to
features of the data.
Revisiting the ggplot function,
we set the size of the points in
the aesthetics function of
the geom_point function to pop.
It's not dramatic, but you can
see that the size of the points
now varies based on
the population size.
What if we wanted to
vary the size of dots by
population and the color
of the dots by some
other criteria.
Let's say we wanted
to vary the color by
some qualitative or
categorical variable.
Again, for practice, we'll
just use the letters here
as stand-ins for
qualitative variables,
and I'll create a string of
letters and attach
them to the data-set.
With a few modifications to
the ggplot function that
should look familiar,
we see that color and
size now are associated
with the categorical variable
and the size of the city.
Note especially here that
I'm setting the color within
the aesthetic function
because I want
the color mapped to a
feature of the data,
whereas before color
was set outside of
the aesthetic function
because I just
wanted every point
to be one color.
Now we just do some quick
practice polishing,
and we're done with the figure
varying both size and
color of the cities.